Guide to the Hill Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hill papers
1695-1709
OSB MSS 31
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
Letters and documents concerning Hill's activities as ambassador to the Hague and envoy to the Savoy. Also includes letters from James Bateman regarding financial matters and political appointments; from James Cressett regarding Cressett's work as a diplomat; from George Dolman regarding the naval maneuvers of the frigate, Lyme, of which Dolman was captain; and from Richard Powys regarding the passing of Hill's bills at the Treasury.
Hill, Richard, 1656?-1727
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Richard Hill.
Diplomatic and consular service, British; Diplomats -- Great Britain; Bateman, James, Sir, d. 1718; Cressett, James, 1655?-1710; Dolman, George, fl. 1705; Hill, Richard, 1656?-1727; Powys, Richard, d. 1724
- Letters and Documents, ca. 1704
  - Anonymous. Account of the Siege of the Gescentin by the French, [n.p.], ca. 1704 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Araciete, Marcos de. 2 ALS to Richard Hill, [n.p.], 1705 Apr 19, 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aremberg, Leopold, Duke of, d. 1754. ALS (in French) to Richard Hill, [n.p.], ca. 1700 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bateman, Sir James, d. 1718
    - 40 ALS and 2 letters (copies) to Richard Hill, Antwerp, London and Helvoetflus, 1696 Jul 4-1701 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      Scope and Contents
      Extensive correspondence on Hill's financial affairs, revealing the interaction between the Bank of England with the Exchequer, Lords of the Treasury, and House of Lords.
    - 8 ALS and 2 letters (copies) to Richard Hill, London, 1697 May 18-1700 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Personal correspondence about financial matters and political appointments.
  - Blackwell, L. ALS to [Richard Hill], Genoa., 1705 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Caracciolo, Antonio. ALS (in Italian) to Richard Hill, [n.p.], 1705 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cressett, James, 1655?-1710
    - 25 ALS and 1 letter (dictated) to Richard Hill, Hamburg, Hanover, and Zell, 1697 Jul 9-1703 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Humorously reveals the lifestyle, disappointments and financial difficulties of an English diplomat.
    - 2 ALS to [Richard Powys], Cheam, 1709 Aug 2, 1709 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - D'Aversberg, Count. ALS (in French) to Richard Hill, [Turin], 1703 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, I. 40.
  - Dolman, George. 4 ALS, 3 LS and 1 letter (copy) to Richard Hill, on board the Lyme, 1705 Apr 2-14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Reports of naval maneuvers from the British frigate, "Lyme," of which Dolman was captain.
  - Frise, Mr. 4 ALS (in French) to Richard Hill, various places, 1695 Jun 12-Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    With references to Mr. Blathwayt.
  - Goetz, Baron. Letter (copy) to William Blathwayt, The Hague, 1694 Jan 19/29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hamilton, Hans, 1652?-. Receipts, signed, Genoa, 1705 Dec 13/24-1706 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Acknowledges receipt of money from Richard Hill for Catalonian Campaign. See Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, II. 688-690.
  - Hill, Richard, 1655-1727
    - AL (draft, in French) to the Dowager-Duchess of Savoy, [n.p.], [1699] Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Sends respects from William III. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, II. 803.
    - AL (draft, in French) to the Duke of Savoy, [n.p.], 1699 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - AL (draft) to M. Vicetti, Genoa, 1706 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Complains about an English sailor being put into chains. Vicetti was Secretary of State of Genoa. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, II. 677 and (translation) II. 912. Accompanied by copy of anonymous letter on same subject, dated 1705 May 4/15.
    - Paper (holograph manuscript, draft) given in by Mr. Hill to the Lord Treasurer, [n.p.], 1706 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Report on the war in Italy. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill.
  - Hop, Mr. Letter (copy, in French) to Lord Villiers, Amsterdam, 1696 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    On payments from the Bank of England.
  - Jeanne de Savoie-Nemours, Duchesse. Letter (copy) to Queen Anne, Turin, 1706 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Welcomes Hill as the Queen's envoy. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, I. 237.
  - Karl VI, Emperor of Germany, 1685- 1740. LS (fragment, in French) to Richard Hill, Barcelona, 1705 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Signature remains, but serious loss of text. Printed in full in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, I. 229 and (translation) II. 875.
  - Letters and Papers concerning the War in Flanders., 1697, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Marlborough, John Churchill, 1st Duke, 1650-1722. LS (fragment, in French) to Richard Hill, from a camp near Landau, 1704 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Signature remains, but serious loss of text. Printed in full in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, I. 169 and (translation) II. 872.
  - Mornay, Mr. 2 ALS (in French) to [Richard Hill?], London, 1703 Apr 11, 24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Netherlands (United Provinces, 1581- 1795) Staten Generaal. Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General, 1704 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Anonymous manuscript (in French). Instructions for Major-General Belcastel; Richard Hill's role in levying 3000 men for protection of Cevennes. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, p. 390, and translated on p. 884.
  - Powys, Richard, d. 1724. 16 ALS to Richard Hill, Whitehall, 1696/7 Feb 9-1705 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    About the passing of Hill's bills at the Treasury while Powys was Paymaster. Matthew Prior is mentioned (1696/7 Feb 9 and Mar 9); Marlborough's victory is reported (1704 Aug 18).
  - Shaw, William. 2 ALS to Richard Hill, [n.p.], 1695 Aug 16, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Fragile, with some loss of text in both letters.
  - Stepney, George, 1663-1707. ALS to Richard Hill, Potsdam, 1699 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Mentions Matthew Prior.
  - Tucker, John
    - 5 ALS to Richard Hill, Whitehall and Cockpit, 1704 Apr 4-Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill. Tucker was an Under-Secretary of State in 1707.
    - 2 ALS to John Chetwynd, Whitehall and Cockpit, 1704 Jul 14, 1704 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Chetwynd was Richard Hill's secretary at the Court of Savoy; later he was on the Board of Trade.
  - William III, King of Gt.Brit., 1650- 1702
    - Letter (copy, in Latin) to the Duke of Savoy, Kensington, 1699 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Letter (copy, in French) to the Dowager-Duchess of Savoy, Kensington, 1699 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, II. 800.
    - Letter (copy, in Latin) to the Duke of Savoy, Kensington, 1699 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Credentials for Richard Hill. Printed in Blackley's Correspondence of Hill, II. 799-800.
  - Copies of letters (partly in cipher) addressed to [Mons. le duc Fengilea], 1705 Apr 19 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters and fragments of letters to unidentified correspondents, 1705, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)